Jean Ritchie and George Pickow collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 1: Manuscripts
  - Subseries 4: Folklore and resources
    - Sub-subseries 2: Folk music and other performing arts resources
      - Correspondence (1/2), 1972-2001 (Box-folder 82/5)
        Correspondence with significant accompanying materials, including photos (relocated to Series 3), drawings, information about the Lydian mode, photocopied pages from published books, a summary report from the "Symposium on marketing phonograph records of American folk expression," "Chordal explorations for 3-string dulcimer" (copyright 1978) and related materials.
      - Correspondence (2/2), 1972-2001 (Box-folder 82/6)
        See the description for box-folder 82/5.
  - Subseries 5: Press coverage
    - Sub-subseries 1: Newspaper clippings, 1920-2009
      A significant number of items are from local newspapers, although a few major newspapers are represented. Some full newspaper sections are included. The older clippings are physically fragile.
      - Reviews and articles (Boxes 83-92)
        Original and photocopied newspaper clippings.
    - Sub-subseries 2: Magazines and pamphlets
      - Complete issues of magazines, 1951 (Box-folder 93)
        Includes local and national publications.
      - Sections from magazines, newsletters, and ephemera, 1980-2009 (Box-folder 94)
        A few items of correspondence accompany some issues.
    - Sub-subseries 3: Clippings and ephemera
      Original and photocopied clippings from newspapers and magazines, plus related correspondence and ephemera. Oversized newspaper clippings have been relocated to boxes 83-94.
      - Reviews, articles, and related ephemera (1/8), 1948-1949 (Box-folder 95/1)
      - Reviews, articles, and related ephemera (2/8), 1950-1959 (Box-folder 95/2)
      - Reviews, articles, and related ephemera (3/8), 1960-1969 (Box-folder 95/3)
      - Reviews, articles, and related ephemera (4/8), 1970-1976 (Box-folder 95/4)
      - Reviews, articles, and related ephemera (5/8), 1980-1988 (Box-folder 95/5)
      - Reviews, articles, and related ephemera (6/8), 1990-1999 (Box-folder 95/6)
      - Reviews, articles, and related ephemera (7/8), 2000-2008, undated (Box-folder 95/7)
      - Reviews, articles, and related ephemera (8/8), undated (Box-folder 95/8)
      - Ecology, strip-mining, etc., 1970-1974, undated (Box-folder 95/9)
  - Subseries 6: Biographical materials
    - Sub-subseries 1: Personal and family history
      - Ritchie family letters and keepsakes, 1894-circa 1920s, undated (Box-folder 96/1)
        Handwritten and typed recollections, color copy of Balis and Abby Ritchie's marriage license, black-and-white photocopy of Balis Ritchie's common school graduation certificate, handwritten notes and a poem, cover for a theatre program and a program, a handwritten letter from Patty to Mallie Ritchie (with a small lock of hair), and locks of hair from Abby and the children, including Jean. The locks of hair and related documents were rehoused by LC Conservation staff in 2017.
      - Ritchie family history (1/4), 1914-1998, undated (Box-folder 96/2)
        A photo of Wilmer Ritchie has been relocated to Series 3.
      - Ritchie family history (2/4), circa 1930s-1999, undated (Box-folder 96/3)
        Copy of a brochure for Pine Mountain Settlement School, handwritten and photocopied recollections, a page about Kentucky quilting party traditions (from Buick magazine), correspondence, printed emails, and various ephemera. Several items of correspondence are from individuals inquiring about a possible family tree connection to Jean.
      - Ritchie family history (3/4), 1922-2004, undated (Box-folder 96/4)
        Handwritten notes on family history, newspaper clippings, typed poems, correspondence from individuals inquiring about a possible family tree connection to Jean, and various handwritten notes.
      - Ritchie family history (4/4), 1935-2006, undated (Box-folder 96/5)
        Correspondence, some combining fan letters and family tree inquiries and information, a printout of a relationship calculator (for family history), a copy of the Christmas card George designed for the first Christmas he and Jean spent together as a married couple, a typed birthday list, copies of Notes from Pine Mountain Settlement School (January 1935, November 1936, and November 1947); and memorial service documents. Photos have been relocated to Series 3.
      - B.W. Ritchie's newspaper, 1908-1910 (Box-folder 96/6)
        Parts of the newspaper B.W. Ritchie published, called variously The record or The news-record. Original section of the front page from vol. 1, no. 35 (December 10, 1908), and the issue from vol. 1, no. 32 (May 12, 1910).
      - Genealogy: correspondence (1/3), 1995-2002 (Box-folder 97/1)
        Primarily correspondence (the majority is printed from email). Also includes printouts of family photos (some scanned and some from the web), various versions of parts of Jean's family tree, family trees and family history.
      - Genealogy: correspondence (2/3), 1995-2002 (Box-folder 97/2)
        See the description for box-folder 97/1.
      - Genealogy: correspondence (3/3), 1995-2002 (Box-folder 97/3)
      - Genealogy: family trees and family stories (1/2), 1961-2002 (Box-folder 97/4)
        Primarily family trees and family history, with some photos (photocopied or printed from scanned images), and correspondence.
      - Genealogy: family trees and family stories (2/2), 1961-2002 (Box-folder 97/5)
        See the description for box-folder 97/4.
      - Jason Ritchie (1/2), 1949-1952, undated (Box-folder 97/6)
        Typed and handwritten notes and lyrics, Jason's handwritten recollections, Jean's handwritten and typed recollection of her notes made on the way to visit Jason in 1949, and correspondence between Jean and Jason. Jason Ritchie, referred to by Jean as "Uncle Jason," was a cousin of Jean's father Balis Ritchie.
      - Jason Ritchie (2/2), 1949-1952, undated (Box-folder 97/7)
        See the description for box-folder 97/6.
      - Balis Ritchie (Box-folder 98/1)
        Typed recollection of a song Balis learned from "Bad Tom" Smith, plus photocopies of published information about Smith, and Balis's obituary from a newspaper (original clipping). Balis was Jean Ritchie's father.
      - Mallie Ritchie (1/2), 1913-circa 1952, undated (Box-folder 98/2)
        Includes correspondence to Mallie, primarily when she was a child while recuperating in the hospital, including picture postcards; a homemade account book, and an illustrated memorial service fan.
      - Mallie Ritchie (2/2), 1930 (Box-folder 98/3)
        Cancelled checques written by Mallie, drawn on The First National Bank (Hazard, Kentucky), and an account statement from the same bank, for December 1930.
      - Una Ritchie, 1923-1971, undated (Box-folder 98/4)
        Correspondence, plus a photocopied article from Vermont life magazine. Photos have been moved to Series 3. Una was one of Jean's sisters.
      - Kitty Ritchie, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 98/5)
        Typed tribute to Kitty, written by Jean, and a page from a 1988 wall calendar, showing Kitty by a corn husk doll. One of Jean's sisters.
      - Edna Ritchie, 1926-1997 (Box-folder 98/6)
        A copy of Viper echoes, a newsletter published by the Viper Public School (February 1926), with a reproduced photo of Edna on the front; a newspaper clipping announcing Edna's marriage, photocopied music, handwritten lyrics, a poem Jean wrote in tribute to Edna (handwritten and typed copies)condolence cards to Jean and other correspondence, memorial handouts, and typed memorial tributes to Edna. One of Jean's sisters.
      - Jewell Ritchie, 1926-1969, undated (Box-folder 98/7)
        Correspondence, a newspaper clipping, a family information questionnaire sent by Jean and partially filled out, Jewel's nursing diploma and other school-related information, Army-related documents and other official documents, a copy of "Singing Up the Moon," written by Jeannie Block (Jewel's daughter), plus a flyer about folk dance camp at Pinewoods. All contents of this folder are photocopies except the questionnaire. Jewel was one of Jean's sisters. Her twin, Opal, died of diphtheria in infancy.
      - Pauline Ritchie, 1935-1980, undated (Box-folder 98/8)
        A memorial program, correspondence, promotional materials for The Lighted Lantern, typed tributes and poems, printed music and lyrics for "Twilight A-Stealin'," The Mountain Echo (vol. 1, no. 3, November 1980; published by the Hindman Settlement School), with a memorial tribute to Pauline, and an essay by Pauline called "Up from the three Rs," published in Wellesley essays (1936). Pauline (also called Polly) was one of Jean's sisters.
      - B.W. Ritchie ("Wilmer" or "Sam"), circa 2003, undated (Box-folder 98/9)
    - Sub-subseries 2: Genealogy, reunions, and education
      - The Ritchie-Cox family episodes: things that actually happened, circa December 2005 (Box-folder 98/10)
        A printed keepsake book, held together with ribbon and with an illustrated cover, of family stories.
      - Knott's gentlefolk and flowers of the forest, vol. 1, nos. 1 and 2, 1995 (Box-folder 98/11)
        Published by the Knott County Historical and Genealogical Society and Library, Inc.
      - Hall family reunions, 1948-2000, undated (Box-folder 99/1)
        Two items of correspondence, reunion programs from 1956, circa 1962, and 2000; two photocopied newspaper clippings, a photocopy of a typed, official greeting from Ronald Reagan to those gathered for the Woodland Jubilee, a typed copy of the Hall family history, and a photocopied, handwritten copy of the family history.
      - Ritchie family reunions (1/2), circa 1975-2003 (Box-folder 99/2)
        Reunion invitations and programs. A photo and a copy negative have been relocated to Series 3.
      - Ritchie family reunions (2/2), 1976-2001 (Box-folder 99/3)
        Correspondence, handwritten notes, memorial programs for Truman Ritchie and Raymond Ritchie, a newspaper clipping, an issue of The Mountain magazine (vol. 1, no. 6, April 1930), an article about corn husk dolls (pages from an unidentified publication), two photocopies of a proclamation declaring June 9-25, 1986 as Ritchie Family Week in Lexington-Fayette, Kentucky, and related ephemera.
      - Early education (1/2), circa 1936-1990 (Box-folder 99/4)
        High school diploma invitations to Jean's high school commencement and to the 1938 commencement, Kentucky Public Schools certificate, 7th grade end-of-year grade report, a copy of The Echo, the Viper High School yearbook, reunion newsletters, correspondence, two napkins from a high school reunion, and a program for the 1939 junior-senior banquet.
      - Early education (2/2), circa 1940 (Box-folder 99/5)
        Copy of The Echo (the Viper High School yearbook).
      - College education (1/2), 1941-2008 (Box-folder 99/6)
        Correspondence, Jean's Cumberland College transcript, periodic grade reports, programs for events, two photocopies of the program for the Cumberland College senior class's play "Junior Miss," an original copy of the program for "February Follies" (presented by the Baptist Student Union of Cumberland College), and related ephemera.
      - College education (2/2), 1941-2008 (Box-folder 99/7)
        See the description for box-folder 99/6.
    - Sub-subseries 3: Promotional biographies, keepsakes, and correspondence
      - Promotional materials (1/5), circa 1951-2008, undated (Box-folder 100/1)
        Biographical and autobiographical materials in various draft stages (mostly typed), correspondence, flyers and brochures, blank letterhead from various organizations, a discography and bibliography for Jean, clippings and newsletters, mock-ups for DVD covers, Folklife Family Store flyers and catalog, business cards for Greenhays, promotional materials from Folkways Records, advertisements for Jean's books and recordings, Jean's membership cards for the Associated Musicians of Greater New York and for the American Federation of Radio Artists, and related ephemera.
      - Promotional materials (2/5), circa 1951-2008, undated (Box-folder 100/2)
        See the note for box-folder 100/1.
      - Promotional materials (3/5), circa 1951-2008, undated (Box-folder 100/3)
      - Promotional materials (4/5), circa 1951-2008, undated (Box-folder 100/4)
      - Promotional materials (5/5), circa 1951-2008, undated (Box-folder 100/5)
      - Transcriptions, scripts, and related documentation, 1958, undated (Box-folder 100/6)
        Handwritten and typed transcriptions from wire recordings, with family members talking and singing, Jean's notes for the Ritchie family album (the Folkways family record), a pencilled drawing of the early Ritchie home place in Viper, a typed draft of a letter to "Peter" (probably Peter Kennedy)
      - George Pickow: biographical materials, 1943-2010 (Box-folder 100/7)
        Orders to report for induction into the military, correspondence, workmen's compensation documents, cancelled cheques and a bank statement, insurance policies, receipts and stubs, a handmade caricature of Jean, George, and Joseph Edwards (a childhood friend of George), news stories about George (original and photocopy), an award of merit from the Advertising Club of New York, medical information, and various permits, passes, and photo IDs.
      - George Pickow: memorabilia, 1947-1950, undated (Box-folder 101/1)
      - Correspondence, including pre-wedding, 1949-1975, undated (Box-folder 101/2)
      - George Pickow's letters while overseas, 1949-1956 (Box-folder 101/3)
        These letters were separate from the letters in box-folder 101/2 and retained as such. Most are letters to Jean but some are to or from George to others.
    - Sub-subseries 4: Awards
      - Berea College honorary Doctor of Arts diploma, May 26, 1991 (Box-folder 101/4)
        Diploma awarded to Jean in 1991, in its presentation folder.
      - Kentucky Country Music Hall of Fame, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 101/5)
        Correspondence, meeting agendas and minutes, Jean was one of the first Board members. The Kentucky Country Music Hall of Fame's name was changed to The Museum of Kentucky Music and Hall of Honor.
      - Awards and related documents (1/2), 1967-2009 (Box-folder 101/6)
        Certificates for Jean, George, and together as a couple, plus correspondence and related documents.
      - Awards and related documents (2/2), 1967-2009 (Box-folder 101/7)
        See the description for box-folder 101/6.
    - Sub-subseries 5: Scrapbooks, journals, and writings
      - Abbie Ritchie's scrapbook, circa 1914-1966, 6 1/8 in. x 9 1/4 in. (Box-folder 102)
        Newspaper clippings, reunion programs, handwritten notes (including one written by Abbie), and related materials. A photo of Abbie holding twin infant daughters Jewel and Opal has been relocated to Series 3. Opal Ritchie died age about 14 months from diphtheria.
      - Scrapbook, circa 1942-1946, undated, 10 1/8 in. x 12 3/4 in. (Box-folder 103)
        Correspondence, napkins, calendars, locks of hair, event programs, newspaper clippings, comics, handwritten documents, and various keepsakes.
      - Scrapbook, circa 1950-1967, undated, 8 3/8 in. x 11 5/8 in. (Box-folder 104)
        Newspaper clippings, flyers and programs for events, and printed poetry.
      - Scrapbook, circa 1929-1957, undated, 12 1/2 in. x 16 1/2 in. (Box-folder 105)
        Newspaper clippings, birth announcements, greeting cards for various holidays, and acknowledgement cards. One of the earliest items is a grade report for Jean, from 1929. The bulk of items dates from the 1950s.
      - School papers, 1922-1924, undated (Box-folder 106/1)
        Four papers written by Jean's sister Una, and one written by Jean's brother Raymond.
      - Abbie Ritchie's handwritten notes, 1960-1969 (Box-folder 106/2)
        Handwritten notes on lined paper removed from a spiral-bound notebook. Includes family information and recollections.
      - 4-H Club memory book with Jean's handwritten notes, 1935-1936 (Box-folder 106/3)
        Handwritten journal entries, recollections and poetry. The last page includes a note that "this was written when I went to camp in July, 1935. Had a grand time. Is now July, 1936 - pleasant memories."
      - Jean's journal and writings, 1944-1948, undated (Box-folder 106/4)
      - Jean's handwritten notes (1/3), 1948-1949 (Box-folder 106/5)
        Jean's notes and reflections on events and people.
      - Jean's handwritten notes (2/3), 1950-1959 (Box-folder 106/6)
        Some of the notes include information about family members, a map of where they live, and related information.
      - Jean's handwritten notes (3/3), 1960-1969 (Box-folder 106/7)
        Diary notes on two large sheets of paper, written while on a trip to France with the Kennedys.
    - Sub-subseries 6: Passports
      Each passport includes a photo of the individual affixed to a page (there is an extra photo of George in one of his passports).
      - Jean Ritchie's U.S. passports, circa 1952-1984 (Box-folder 106/8)
        Seven passports, with issue dates of 1952, 1956, 1960, 1966, 1971, 1978, and 1984.
      - George Pickow's U.S. passports, circa 1944-1994 (Box-folder 106/9)
        Seven passports, with issue dates of 1944, 1948, 1952, 1960, 1971, 1978, and 1994.
    - Sub-subseries 7: Engagement books and calendars
      Each item includes handwritten notes regarding appointments and activities.
      - Engagement books and calendars, 1947-1949, 2 in. x 3 in. (Box-folder 106/10)
        3 appointment books.
      - Engagement books and calendars (1/2), 1950-1959, From 2 in. x 3 in. to 6 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 106/11)
        10 items, total. A 1959-1960 engagement book for George Pickow includes two business cards.
      - Engagement books and calendars (2/2), 1950-1959, From 2 in. x 3 in. to 6 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 107/1)
        See the description for box-folder 106/11.
      - Engagement books and calendars (1/3), 1960-1969, From 2 in. x 3 in. to 8 3/4 in. x 11 in. (Box-folder 107/2)
        15 items total (from the 1960s). Some years are represented by multiple items. A 1963 wall calendar has 4 sheets of handwritten notes for accounting.
      - Engagement books and calendars (2/3), 1960-1969, From 2 in. x 3 in. to 8 3/4 in. x 11 in. (Box-folder 107/3)
        See the description for box-folder 107/2.
      - Engagement books and calendars (3/3), 1960-1969, From 2 in. x 3 in. to 8 3/4 in. x 11 in. (Box-folder 107/4)
      - Engagement books and calendars (1/2), 1970-1978, From 2 3/4 in. x 4 1/4 in. to 9 1/4 in. x 10 3/4 in. (Box-folder 107/5)
        12 items total (from the 1970s). Some items represent an overlap of years. No item for 1979.
      - Engagement books and calendars (2/2), 1970-1978, From 2 3/4 in. x 4 1/4 in. to 9 1/4 in. x 10 3/4 in. (Box-folder 107/6)
        See the description for box-folder 107/5.
      - Engagement books and calendars, 1984-1989, From 3 in. x 4 1/2 in. to 7 3/4 in. x 10 1/2 in. (Box-folder 108/1)
        5 items. Years represented: 1984, 1985, 1987-1989. Two items for 1988. See box 109 for another 2005 calendar.
      - Engagement books and calendars (1/2), 1990-1992, 1994, From 4 in. x 6 in. to 8 1/2 in. x 11 in. (Box-folder 108/2)
        13 items. No item for 1993. Multiple items for some years. The 1996-1997 calendar is a custom printing, with a black plastic comb binding and reproductions (black and white and color) of Ritchie family photos. See box 109 109 the 1998 wall calendar.
      - Engagement books and calendars (2/2), 1990-1992, 1994, From 4 in. x 6 in. to 8 1/2 in. x 11 in. (Box-folder 108/3)
        See the description for box-folder 108/2.
      - Engagement books and calendars (1/3), 2000-2003, 2005, From 3 3/4 in. x 5 1/2 in. to 8 3/4 in. x 11 in. (Box-folder 108/4)
        22 items, total. Multiple items for some years. A few loose pages from a 2007 calendar. One item is a customized 2001 pocket calendar, stamped "Compliments of Folklife Productions" (Jean and George's company). See box 109 for calendars from 2006 and 2007.
      - Engagement books and calendars (2/3), 2000-2003, 2005, From 3 3/4 in. x 5 1/2 in. to 8 3/4 in. x 11 in. (Box-folder 108/5)
        See the description for box-folder 108/4.
      - Engagement books and calendars (3/3), 2000-2003, 2005, From 3 3/4 in. x 5 1/2 in. to 8 3/4 in. x 11 in. (Box-folder 108/6)
      - Wall calendars, circa 1985-2007, From 10 in. x 10 3/4 in. to 12 in. x 12 in. Years represented: 1985, 1998, 2002, 2006-2007. (Box-folder 109)
    - Sub-subseries 8: Diaries
      - Diaries and notes about events, 1922-1992, undated, From 2 3/4 in. x 4 1/2 in. to 5 1/4 in. x 8 1/2 in. (Box-folder 110)
        Some of the fifteen items are repurposed notepads and records books. Some items are clearly identified as written by Jean and some by Jean's family members: Abbie, Kitty, and Mallie Ritchie. Some items were used by more than one individual. Of note: Kitty Ritchie's 1925 notes has a four-leaf clover pinned to one page.
    - Sub-subseries 9: Ritchie family hymnals
      - Billups, Edward W. The sweet songster: a collection of the most popular and approved songs, hymns, and ballads. Catlettsburg, KY: C.L. McConnell, circa 1854 (Box-folder 111/1)
      - Thomas, E.D. A new and choice selection of hymns and spiritual songs for the use of the Regular Baptist Church, and all lovers of song. Catlettsburg, KY: C.L. McConnell, circa 1877 (Box-folder 111/2)
  - Subseries 7: George Pickow's photographic work
    - Sub-subseries 1: Album covers
      Dust jackets for a selection of phonographic albums recorded by Jean Ritchie. The cover photographs (and sometimes the jacket designs) are by George Pickow.
      - Jean Ritchie, 1952, 1954 (Box 112)
        Elektra Records; EKL-125.
      - Carols of all seasons, 1959 (Box 112)
        Tradition Records; TLP 1031
      - Children's songs and games from the southern mountains, 1957, 1960 (Box 112)
        Folkways Records; FC 7054.
      - As I Roved Out (Field Trip-Ireland), 1960 (Box 112)
        Folkways Records; FW 8872
      - Clear waters remembered, 1974 (Box 112)
        Geordie Music; Geordie 101. Two copies.
      - Jean Ritchie at home, 1974 (Box 112)
        Pacific Cascade Records; LPL 7026
      - None but one, 1977 (Box 112)
        Sire Records; SA 7530. Two copies.
      - High hills and mountains, 1979 (Box 112)
        Greenhays Recordings; catalog number GR 701. Two copies.
      - Sweet rivers, 1981 (Box 112)
        June Appal Recordings; JA-037.
      - None but one, 1981 (Box 112)
        Greenhays Recordings; GR 708.
      - The most dulcimer, 1992 (Box 112)
        Greenhays Recordings; catalog number GR 714.
      - Kentucky Christmas: old and new, 1997 (Box 112)
        Greenhays Recordings; GR 717
    - Sub-subseries 2: Proofs for album covers
      Album jackets from this era were frequently made of cardboard, with a glossy sheet affixed to the front (and sometimes the back), with the album title and artist, and usually an illustration. These are the glossy sheets, most for popular and folk music, but some for classical music. Two covers are printed on heavy-stock paper boards. George took the photos and in some cases may have designed the covers.
      - Proofs for album covers (box 1 of 3) (Box-folder 113)
        See the note for Sub-subseries 2.
      - Proofs for album covers (box 2 of 3) (Box-folder 114)
      - Proofs for album covers (box 3 of 3) (Box-folder 115)
    - Sub-subseries 3: Magazine covers and related materials